Federico Cipriani

federico.cipriani at linux.com · GitHub · LinkedIn

View This Resume on My Website

Summary

Lifelong, passionate programmer with 4 years as a full-stack developer and almost 4 years as a DevOps/SRE and FinOps. I am a hardcore Linux user with nearly a decade of experience in Arch Linux and several years as a dedicated NixOS user.

Education

Electronic Technician

Otto Krause · Buenos Aires, Argentina

Space Systems Engineering

Universidad Nacional de San Martín (UNSAM) · Buenos Aires, Argentina

Languages

I am an EU citizen (Italian) with native proficiency in Spanish and C2 proficiency in English.

Experience

Site Reliability Engineer

Yuno · Hybrid: Buenos Aires, Argentina & Bogotá, Colombia

06/2022 - 11/2024

- Terraforming multiple AWS accounts, with network peering for multiple purposes.
- · Provisioning and maintaining several EKS clusters, alongside managing their service mesh.
- Adopted Datadog, providing instrumentation while controlling data ingestion and costs.
- Proactively met weekly to analyze cloud spending and plan FinOps automation strategies.
- Engaged with cloud provider teams to assess technical and cost-fit solutions for our needs.
- Designed dashboards and monitors for SLOs, collaborating on SLI definitions with various teams.
- Implemented near real-time Change Data Capture (CDC) pipelines for the Data team's BI needs.
- Co-led Reliability Track sessions, using Testkube to stress test and boost core product performance.
- Developed several FastAPI backends to integrate Argo, AWS, Datadog, Kubernetes, Opsgenie, and Slack.

Site Reliability Engineer

Agot AI · Hybrid: Buenos Aires, Argentina & Pittsburgh, US

03/2021 - 05/2022

- Provisioning a hybrid on-premise cloud with K3S on Nvidia Jetson.
- Review and refactoring of technology stacks in both FrontEnd and BackEnd areas.
- Quality control and code sanitization of all projects through GitLab CI pipeline jobs (ShellCheck, Pytest, etc).
- Research and benchmarking of cloud-based Machine Learning training tools (SageMaker, MLFlow, and Kubeflow).
- Inference box servers budget & compatibility planning for on-premise instances.

Software Engineer

Democracia en Red (DeR) · Remote: Buenos Aires, Argentina

11/2020 - 04/2021

- Development of full-stack solutions with Svelte and FastAPI technologies for a civic software platform.
- Integration with Blockchain Federal Argentina (BFA) Proof of Authority (PoA) network for an e-voting system.
- Prototyping, implementation, and maintenance of standardized solutions.

Software Engineer

Nevrona · Remote: Buenos Aires, Argentina

04/2019 - 12/2020

- Served as Lead Developer and Architect for the FrontEnd & Middleware team.
- Co-led development of a comprehensive work and social networking platform from inception.
- Designed and built administrative interface (backoffice) for platform management.
- Authored technical documentation and established FrontEnd and general development guidelines.
- Conducted technical interviews and recruitment for both BackEnd and FrontEnd teams.

System Administrator & SWE

APLI · On-site: Buenos Aires, Argentina

05/2017 - 12/2019

- Remote and on-site support of server infrastructure.
- Development of scripts and utilities for the shell in Bash, Perl, and Python.
- Monitoring and alarm systems with Nagios, Icinga, Nagstamon, and Prometheus.
- I've built a Raspberry-based monitor wall for a Network Operation Center (NOC).

Licenses & Certifications

I currently hold the following certified exams and courses:

- HashiCorp Certified: Terraform Associate (003).
- Linux Foundation: Certified Argo Project Associate (CAPA).
- Linux Foundation: Certified GitOps Associate (CGOA).
- Linux Foundation: Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA).
- Linux Foundation: Kubernetes and Cloud Native Associate (KCNA).
- Linux Foundation: Kubernetes and Cloud Native Security Associate (KCSA).
- Linux Foundation: Ethics for Open Source Development (LFC104).
- Linux Foundation: Developing Secure Software (LFD121).
- Linux Foundation: Security Self-Assessments for Open Source Projects (LFEL1005).
- Linux Foundation: Securing Projects with OpenSSF Scorecard (LFEL1006).
- Linux Foundation: Automating Supply Chain Security SBOMs and Signatures (LFEL1007).
- Linux Foundation: Scaling Cloud Native Applications with KEDA (LFEL1014).
- Linux Foundation: XSS Exploits and Defenses (LFEL1010).

Skillset

Cloud & Infrastructure

Ansible, Argo, AWS Ecosystem (ACM, CE, CloudWatch, CodeArtifact, EC2, ECR, ElastiCache, EKS, IAM, KMS, Lambda, RDS, Route53, S3, Secrets Manager, SQS, VPC), CI/CD, FinOps, Infrastructure as Code (IaC), Istio, GitOps, Github Actions, Helm, Kustomize, Kubernetes, K3S, KEDA, NixOS, Service Mesh, Terraform, Terragrunt, Testkube, Velero.

Monitoring & Reliability

Alertmanager, Business Continuity Plan (BCP), Chaos Mesh, Datadog, Fluentd, Grafana, Prometheus, Obersvability Instrumentation, Incident Response Management, Opsgenie, Post Mortem Writing, Chaos Engineering, RPO/RTO, Statuspage, Stress Testing.

Security & Compliance

AIDE, CVEs/CWEs, Encryption, GDPR, HIDS/NIDS, LUKS, NIST Compliance, MITRE ATT&CK, Nmap, OWASP, PCIDSS, SAST, SBOMs, STRIDE, Security Self-Assessment, TCPDump/LibPCap, WAF, Wireshark, Zero Trust Architecture.

Data Engineering

Airbyte, CDC, DVC, DynamoDB, ElasticSearch, ELT/ETL, Kafka, Kubeflow, MLOps, MSK, MySQL, MWAA, PeerDB, PostgreSQL, SageMaker.

Programming & Frameworks

ACID, Axum, CLEAN, CQRS, Deno, Express/Polka, FastAPI, Haskell, Nix/Flakes, NodeJS, Python, Rust, Shell, Svelte/Kit, Typer, Typescript.

Work Culture & Practices

Agile, Architecture Design Records (ADRs), Follow-The-Sun (GDSE), KPI/OKR Alignment, Async communication, Meeting Minutes & Outcome-Based Agendas.